[Road to Success]
[찬여번성: 별처럼 빛나리]
[Episode 14]
[제14화]
It might hurt a little.
좀 아플 수도 있어요
Because his heart
그래도 마음은
is already here.
이미 여기 와 있어요
What?
네?
I mean Wen Chengye.
원청예 말이에요
He may still be a bit resistant,
아직 거부감이 있긴 하지만
but he came anyway.
결국 왔잖아요
Because his heart is already here.
마음은 이미 여기 와 있다고요
Done.
됐어요
Thank you.
고마워요
It's going to rain. Let's put the books away.
비 올 것 같은데 책부터 챙기죠
It's starting to drizzle.
이제 빗방울이 떨어지기 시작했네요
You look like you're actually enjoying this.
꽤 즐기는 것 같은데요?
Yeah.
맞아요
Hongjing is by the sea,
훙징은 바다를 끼고 있고
and I grew up here.
난 훙징 사람이니까요
Getting caught in the rain is just part of everyday life.
여기선 비 맞는 게 일상이에요
The rain suddenly started pouring. Maybe we should...
비가 막 쏟아지려는데, 우리…
Too late. Run!
늦었어요, 뛰어요!
♪ I caught your eyes ♪
♪ 난 네 눈빛을 포착했어 ♪
♪ On the summer night ♪
♪ 그 여름밤에 ♪
♪ Like stars that glow so bright ♪
♪ 눈부시게 반짝이던 별처럼 ♪
I
난
don't hate rainy days anymore.
이젠 비 오는 날이 싫지 않다
♪ A spark in my heart ♪
♪ 마음속 한 떨기의 불꽃이 ♪
♪ Lost in a dream secretly ♪
♪ 꿈속에서 조용히 사라져 갔어 ♪
Because...
왜냐면…
♪ With the evening breeze whispering in my ear ♪
♪ 저녁 바람이 귓가에 고백을 전하면 ♪
♪ Fireworks bloom across the sky ♪
♪ 하늘 가득 불꽃이 피어나고 ♪
♪ Shimmering in your eyes ♪
♪ 그 빛이 네 눈동자에 비치면 ♪
Come on, slow down.
조심해요
♪ And spreading into a gentle sea of stars ♪
♪ 따스한 별 바다로 번져 가 ♪
Watch the stairs. Be careful.
계단 조심해요
What are you laughing at?
왜 웃어요?
I'm laughing at you.
웃겨서요
You've probably never looked this disheveled before.
이렇게 엉망이었던 적 없죠?
Hold still.
움직이지 마요
Your eyes are so important.
코치님 눈이 얼마나 중요한데
We can't let anything get in them.
뭐가 들어가면 안 되죠
I thought it was something serious.
난 또 뭐라고
You've got raindrops on your eyelashes.
속눈썹에 물이 고였어요
Your eyes are also very important, Ms. Lin.
린 선생님 눈도 중요하잖아요
Hurry and take a hot shower.
따뜻한 물로 샤워나 해요
Don't catch a cold.
감기 걸리지 않게
[Director Qian]
[첸 주임님]
Lin,
린 선생님
you can get a temporary pass
코치한테 임시 출입증 만들어 주는 건
for Coach Wang.
문제없어요
Just create an account for him in the school system.
학교 시스템에 등록만 하면 되니까
Also, keep the monthly exam
그리고 월간 고사
in mind.
꼭 신경 써요
Understood. Thank you, Director.
알겠습니다, 정말 감사해요
[Hongjing No. 8 High School]
[훙징시 제8고등학교]
[This account is already registered. Please enter a different one.]
[이미 등록된 계정입니다 다시 입력해 주세요]
I need another number...
새 계정이 필요하네
Oh, right.
아, 맞다
I have another QQ account.
나 QQ 계정 하나 더 있지
[This account is already registered. Please enter a different one.]
[이미 등록된 계정입니다 다시 입력해 주세요]
[Phone Number/Email/QQ]
[핸드폰, 번호 메일, QQ]
[Username: Wang Fa]
[닉네임 왕파]
[Password] [Your password is too short. Please choose a new password.]
[비밀번호] [비밀번호가 너무 짧습니다 새 비밀번호를 생각해 주세요]
[Your password is weak.]
[비밀번호 매우 약합니다]
[Your password is not strong enough.]
[비밀번호가 강하지 않습니다]
[Hello, Mr. Wang Fa.]
[왕파선생님, 안녕하세요]
Coach Wang,
코치님
I hope this unrestricted campus access pass
이 출입증으로 학교를 자유롭게 드나들면서
gives you a sense of belonging.
조금이나마 소속감을 느끼셨으면 좋겠네요
[Slack Superstar]
[느긋한 초신성]
I got your access pass sorted out.
출입증 나왔어요
♪ Night slips through my fingers ♪
♪ 밤은 손가락 틈새로 흘러 ♪
♪ Embracing the coldness of wakefulness ♪
♪ 깨어 있는 차가움을 감싸고 ♪
♪ Whispering my thoughts alone ♪
♪ 홀로 마음을 속삭이며 ♪
♪ Saying goodbye to the evening breeze we met by chance ♪
♪ 우연히 마주친 밤바람과 작별하네 ♪
♪ Staying with the jasmine blossoms until late spring ♪
♪ 늦봄이 올 때까지 재스민 곁을 지키니 ♪
♪ Watching their elegance fade, their fragrance disappear ♪
♪ 우아하게 바래 가는 싱그러운 향기 ♪
♪ I once dreamed of beauty ♪
♪ 아름다운 것들과 꿈을 꾸었기에 ♪
The rain in Hongjing is beautiful.
훙징의 비가 참 예쁘네요
♪ And I accept that regrets may grow wild ♪
♪ 아쉬움이 피어나는 것도 받아들이네 ♪
[The rain in Hongjing is beautiful.]
[훙징의 비가 참 예쁘네요]
♪ Look, beneath the sunlight ♪
♪ 바라봐, 햇살 아래 ♪
♪ In the dancing specks of dust ♪
♪ 기쁘게 춤추는 미세한 먼지들을 ♪
♪ I'm grateful I never lost my sincerity ♪
♪ 다행히도 잃은 적은 없었지 진지함과 ♪
[Slack Superstar]
[느긋한 초신성]
How about I teach you how to ride a bike sometime?
기회가 되면 자전거 가르쳐 줄게요
♪ Or my gift for happiness ♪
♪ 행복의 재능을 ♪
What beautiful rain?
비가 예뻐?
♪ In the rain ♪
♪ 한바탕 비와 ♪
Messaging Ms. Lin, huh?
린 선생님이랑 문자 하네?
I never should've given you the key to my place.
우리 집 열쇠 뺏어야겠네
You've fallen for her.
너 빠졌구나?
You actually hesitated.
망설이네?
Don't you have anything better to do?
할 짓이 그렇게 없냐?
Is Hengjiu Club really paying you to sit around like this?
헝주 돈이 그렇게 벌기 쉬워?
Now that's a classic change of subject.
이거 봐, 말 돌리는 거
Tell you what.
이렇게 하자
Let me help you out.
린 선생님이랑 잘되게
I'll help you win her over.
내가 가르쳐 줄게
You?
네가?
[Slack Superstar]
[느긋한 초신성]
Up for a drink?
술 한잔할래?
Bring out the good stuff, and I'm in.
좋은 술 가져오면 마셔야지
Very good stuff.
죽이는 술이야
That's more like it.
이제야 좀 말이 통하네
Overall, this book
이 책은
covers famous
유명한 역사적 인물의
historical figures,
이름이랑
key moments in history, and historical facts.
중요한 역사적 시점 및 사실에 대해 다루고 있어요
It's essentially a narrative-style history book.
이야기 형식의 역사책이죠
Very good.
아주 좋아
Thank you, Ms. Lin.
감사합니다
Let's begin class.
수업 시작하자
-So? -How'd it go?
- 어때?
Did you pass?
통과했어?
-Did you pass? -Nailed it.
- 통과했어? - 치워
Here she comes.
수업이다
You've all finished today's reading
오늘의 읽기 과제와 복습
and oral retelling assignment.
다들 잘 완성했어
The purpose of this exercise
이건 주로 집중력을
is to improve your concentration.
올려 주는 연습인데
Learning is a game of efficiency.
공부라는 게 결국 효율 싸움이거든
Congratulations, everyone, on completing Lesson One.
첫 수업 잘 완수한 걸 축하한다
Next, I'd like to ask you a question.
그럼 이제 질문 하나 할게
Why do you want to improve?
다들 왜 발전하고 싶어?
Because if we don't do well on the next monthly exam,
월간 고사를 망치면
we won't be allowed to play football.
축구 못 하잖아요
-Right. We want to keep playing football. -Play football.
- 맞아요, 계속 축구 하고 싶어요 - 축구하고 싶어요
-Right. We want to play football.
- 축구 하고 싶습니다 - 축구 하려고요
Very good.
좋아
Interest.
흥미
-Interest.
- 흥미
-Drive.
동기부여
-Feedback.
피드백
What does that mean?
무슨 뜻이지?
-No idea. -I don't know.
- 몰라 - 모르겠어
Feedback.
피드백?
Next, let's move on to
자, 그럼 이제
the second lesson of Yuanyuan's Classroom.
위안위안 공부방의 두 번째 수업을 시작할게
Interest is the greatest driving force.
흥미는 첫 번째 동기부여야
Let me ask you something.
생각해 봐
When you're introduced
너희가 잘 모르는 것을
to something unfamiliar,
처음 접하게 됐을 때
what's your first reaction?
드는 느낌은 뭐야?
Fear, I guess.
두려움이요
Exactly,
맞아
scared.
두려움
So today, I want you to learn to start from
그래서 오늘은
what you're familiar with
자신이 익숙하고
and what interests you,
흥미를 느끼는 것부터 시작해서
and use scientific learning methods to make progress.
과학적인 학습 방법으로 발전하는 법을 배울 거야
Ms. Lin, how do we start
선생님, 익숙하고 흥미를 느끼는 것부터
from something we're familiar with and interested in?
시작한다는 게 어떤 건가요?
Do you know
사람들이
what people usually learn first when studying
각 나라의 언어나 사투리를 배울 때
a foreign language or a dialect?
가장 먼저 뭘 배우는지 알아?
Swear words, of course.
당연히 욕이죠
-Let's do Classical Chinese insults. -Insults?
- 좋아, 문언문 욕부터 배워 보자 - 욕이래
Can anyone think of some that everybody knows?
다들 익숙한 거 있으면
Go ahead.
말해 봐
Chen Jianghe.
천장허
"R-Rotten wood cannot be carved;
썩, 썩은 나무로는 조각할 수 없다
a wall of dung cannot be plastered."
썩은 담장은 덧칠할 수 없다
Qin Ao.
친아오
I'll allow you to look it up.
검색해도 돼
Looks like what I just said fits you perfectly.
방금 내가 한 말이 너한테 딱이네
You rotten wood.
썩은 나무
I'll look something up too.
나도 찾아봐야지
"This brat is not worthy of conspiring over important matters."
수자부족여모
Explain it.
뜻 설명해 봐
It means,
그러니까
"A stupid boy like you doesn't deserve to discuss strategy with me."
멍청한 놈이랑은 같이 할 게 못 된다는 뜻이에요
"People say Chu men are just monkeys wearing hats."
사람들이 초나라 사람은 원숭이가 관 쓴 격이라더니
You're indeed all show—
역시 넌 겉만 번지르르한 놈이었어
literally a monkey in a hat.
원숭이가 모자 쓴 격이네
Poser.
실속이 없어
Just you wait.
너 딱 기다려
"Shameless and scheming,
승영구구
returning like driven flies."
구거부환
You're a petty opportunist, buzzing around like a fly,
파리처럼 빌붙고
clinging to life like a mangy dog!
개처럼 구차하게 목숨을 부지하는 놈아
"You, gaunt as a turtledove, sallow as a starving crane,
구형곡면지도 같은 놈이
how dare you speak such nonsense?"
어디서 망언을 퍼부어?
Make one up. Insult him back.
직접 문장 만들어서 욕해봐
He just called you skinny as a turtledove,
비둘기처럼 바싹 마르고
with a face as pale as a starving crane—
거위처럼 얼굴이 하얗다는 뜻이야
weak and ugly.
약하고 못생겼단 얘기지
Just you wait.
너 기다려
Come on. Come on.
해봐, 어디
Too weak.
넌 너무 약해
Got it.
찾았다!
With the head of a muntjac and the eyes of a rat,
노루 머리에 쥐 눈을 가진 놈
you can only be up to no good!
딱 봐도 나쁜 놈이야
I can insult people in Classical Chinese now!
나 이제 문언문으로 욕할 줄 알아
That's progress.
발전했네
You brat!
이놈아!
Impressive, impressive.
대단해
You, a pile of dry bones in a grave—
무덤 속 썩은 뼈 따위가
hardly worth worrying about.
뭐 신경 쓸 가치가 있냐?
He really learned it.
진짜 잘하네
He really did.
잘해
Impressive.
진짜 대단하다
Qin Ao, you memorized it
친아오 너 한 글자도 안 틀리고
word for word.
다 외웠네
You've grown up.
많이 컸다
Amazing, amazing.
- 대단해
Let's give Qin Ao a round of applause.
친아오 박수쳐 주자
Very good.
제법이야
[Math, Physics, Chemistry] [Chinese]
[수학, 물리, 화학] [국어]
You should all know
다들 알다시피
it's clearly impossible to
단기간에
raise your grades in every subject
모든 과목의 점수를 올리는 건
in such a short period of time.
불가능한 일이야
[Math, Physics, Chemistry] [Chinese]
[수학, 물리, 화학] [국어]
The first three multi-step questions in math,
수학, 물리, 화학 서술형 앞 세 문제는
physics, and chemistry cover concepts that are relatively simple.
비교적 간단한 편이라
We can master them
문제 풀이랑
through practice problems and memorizing formulas.
공식 암기를 통해서 마스터할 수 있어
They are basically free points.
거저 주는 문제나 다름없지
There's another area.
그리고 또 하나
[Math, Physics, Chemistry] [Chinese]
[수학, 물리, 화학] [국어]
The Classical Chinese section on the Chinese exam
국어 문언문 문제도
is also one of the easiest places to gain
비교적
the most points with the least effort.
점수를 올리기 쉬운 부분이야
[Math, Physics, Chemistry] [Chinese]
[수학, 물리, 화학] [국어]
By breaking through these two sections—
이 두 가지를 공략하면 돼
using interest as your driving force,
방금 가르쳐 준 것처럼
like I just taught you—
흥미를 원동력으로
you can tap into your own potential.
자신의 잠재력을 발휘해 봐
Look straight ahead.
고개 들고 앞을 봐요
You have to hold on to my bike, okay?
꼭 잘 잡아 줘야 해요
Relax.
걱정 마요
Keep the handlebars straight.
핸들 똑바로, 핸들 똑바로
Turn right.
오른쪽
To the right.
오른쪽으로요
Your right hand.
오른손
That's it. Rest it on the brake lever.
맞아요, 브레이크 위에 올려요
Not that hand. Right hand. Right.
아니, 오른손이요, 오른손
This is left. Your right hand.
이건 왼쪽이고 오른손 쓰라고요
Pick up a little speed.
속도 좀 낼게요
Straighten the handlebars.
핸들 똑바로
Promise you won't let go!
나 좀 잘 잡아 줘요
Don't let me fall!
넘어지면 안 돼요
Relax. I've got you.
걱정 마요, 잡고 있으니까요
There's a bridge ahead. I can't make it up.
앞에 다리가 있어서 못 올라가겠어요
Then try turning.
그럼 방향 틀어 봐요
To the left.
왼쪽으로요
I'm tipping over. I'm falling!
넘어질 것 같아요
I've got you.
내가 있잖아요
I turned.
돌렸어요
Keep your eyes forward.
앞을 봐요
-Speed up. -I think I'm getting the hang of it.
- 속도 낼게요 - 이제 감이 좀 잡혀요
Good job, Ms. Lin.
아주 잘하고 있어요
You absolutely cannot let go.
절대 손 놓으면 안 돼요
Don't worry. I won't.
걱정 마요, 안 놔요
I learned it.
됐어요
I learned it!
저 이제 탈 줄 알아요
♪ Time's passing by ♪
♪ 세월은 물처럼 ♪
♪ Nothing remains ♪
♪ 흔적도 없이 흘러가고 ♪
Wang Fa.
코치님
You let go!
손 놨죠?
♪ All the dreamers awake alone ♪
♪ 함께 꿈꾸던 우리 쉽사리 잠들지 못하네 ♪
I learned it.
저 이제 탈 줄 알아요
Congratulations.
축하해요
♪ Shadows above ♪
♪ 때로는 먹구름이 드리우고 ♪
From now on, it'll be my turn to give you rides.
다음엔 내가 태워 줄게요
♪ Rain falls around ♪
♪ 축축한 빗물이 삶의 구석구석을 적셔도 ♪
Ms. Lin's got big ambitions.
야망이 대단한데요?
Then I'll look forward to it.
기대하고 있을게요
♪ In your arms ♪
♪ 네 품 안에서 ♪
♪ We become one ♪
♪ 평행하던 우리 세상은 마침내 하나가 돼 ♪
♪ Through day and night ♪
♪ 낮과 밤이 흘러도 ♪
♪ I can see you ♪
♪ 너의 눈동자 속에서 ♪
♪ In my eyes ♪
♪ 진짜 나를 마주해 ♪
♪ Just hold me tight ♪
♪ 꼭 안아 주기만 하면 ♪
♪ Look into my soul so deeply ♪
♪ 너의 시선은 내 영혼 깊숙이 닿아 ♪
♪ Rainbow sunlight ♪
♪ 무지갯빛 후광 아래 ♪
♪ Painful tears are gone ♪
♪ 아픈 지난날은 어제가 되고 ♪
♪ Wonderful dreams ♪
♪ 반짝이는 아름다운 꿈은 ♪
♪ Are so close to me ♪
♪ 내게는 닿을 수 없는 것 같지만 ♪
♪ Memories fly ♪
♪ 추억은 스쳐 가는 한숨처럼 ♪
♪ Leave them all behind ♪
♪ 지난 상처를 다정히 어루만지고 ♪
♪ Just take my hand and stay with me ♪
♪ 우리는 손을 맞잡은 채 영원히 함께해 ♪
♪ Two souls aligned ♪
♪ 두 영혼이 서로 기대어 ♪
♪ In silent gravity ♪
♪ 말 없는 끌림 속에 머무네 ♪
[Studied in the UK; psychology major]
[영국 유학생, 심리학 전공]
[Loves spicy food; hates coriander]
[매운 걸 좋아하고 고수는 싫어함]
♪ Heal my heart ♪
♪ 너의 모든 것으로 ♪
♪ With every part of you ♪
♪ 내 모든 외로움을 치유해 ♪
Have you ever heard of drinking wontons?
완탕 마셔본 적 있어요?
For wontons like these, with thin wrappers and just a little filling,
이렇게 피가 얇고 소가 작은 완탕은
♪ Our words flow ♪
♪ 말들은 잔잔히 흘러 ♪
you can just drink them with the soup.
국물이랑 같이 마실 수 있어요
♪ A gentle stream ♪
♪ 부드러운 시냇물처럼 ♪
[Bad at sports; can't ride a bike]
[운동을 잘 못하고 자전거도 못 탐]
♪ They glow like fireflies ♪
♪ 반딧불처럼 희미한 빛이 ♪
This is called cheating.
이건 부정행위예요
♪ Inside a silken dream ♪
♪ 포근한 꿈으로 스며들어 ♪
What do you know?
뭘 모르시네요
This is called strategic intelligence.
이걸 지혜라고 하는 거예요
[Fireflies expert]
[반딧불이 전문가]
♪ We talk the cool night, breeze away ♪
♪ 밤새 이야기를 나누면 저녁 바람도 사라지고 ♪
But when they gather together,
한데 모이면
they light the way for those moving forward.
앞서가는 사람들의 길을 밝혀주기도 해요
And with their tiny glimmers,
자신의 작은 불빛으로
♪ We trace the roads ♪
♪ 끝없이 이어지는 ♪
they show that every life has value.
생명의 가치를 보여주고요
♪ That never see an end ♪
♪ 먼 길을 같이 걸어가 ♪
[Advocates natural selection]
[자연선택을 숭상함]
[Computer ID: Spade Q] [Highly competitive]
[컴퓨터 이름 스페이드 Q 승부욕 강함]
♪ We softly calm the hidden doubt ♪
♪ 서로의 눈 속 망설임을 ♪
♪ Seen in each other's eyes ♪
♪ 살며시 어루만지네 ♪
♪ And wake the warmth inside ♪
♪ 마음 깊은 곳에 숨겨 둔 온기를 다시 깨워 ♪
Go, Hongjing No. 8 High School!
훙징 제8고, 파이팅
♪ Life begins alone ♪
♪ 인생은 원래 홀로 떠나는 거야 ♪
♪ A road we walk alone ♪
♪ 혼자 걷는 궤적이지 ♪
[Spade Q—Lin Wanxing] [Probability: 0%]
[스페이드 Q 린완싱일 가능성 0%]
[Advocates natural selection]
[자연선택을 숭상함]
♪ Until fate brings warmth ♪
♪ 운명이 따뜻함을 보내 주는 순간까지 ♪
Now there are so many people and things...
지금은 아쉬운 게 많아
♪ To light our way back home ♪
♪ 귀로의 방향을 비춰줘 ♪
I can't bear to let go of.
내려놓을 수 없는 사람과 일 때문에
♪ True love is not just ♪
♪ 진정한 사랑은 ♪
♪ The gaze when two hearts first meet ♪
♪ 첫 만남 그 순간의 눈맞춤이 아니라 ♪
Even though
비록
♪ It's courage in the arms ♪
♪ 서로를 껴안을 때의 단단한 용기야 ♪
I don't really want you to go,
코치님이 떠나는 걸 바라진 않지만
I've decided that whether you stay
코치님이 떠나든 남든
or leave,
난 결정했어요
I'll lead them and help them keep playing their best.
애들 데리고 계속 열심히 축구할 거예요
♪ We stand as one ♪
♪ 우린 함께 의지해 ♪
♪ Our words flow ♪
♪ 말들은 잔잔히 흘러 ♪
[Spade Q—Lin Wanxing] [Probability: 0%]
[스페이드 Q 린완싱일 가능성 0%]
♪ A gentle stream ♪
♪ 부드러운 시냇물처럼 ♪
♪ They glow like fireflies ♪
♪ 반딧불처럼 희미한 빛이 ♪
♪ Inside a silken dream ♪
♪ 포근한 꿈으로 스며들어 ♪
What does this classical text mean?
이 문언문 무슨 뜻이야?
The annotation only says this:
주석에 이것만 쓰여 있어
"Zhang" means "grow."
장, 생장
Do you know what it means?
무슨 뜻인지 알아?
I don't know either.
나도 몰라
Just look it up on your phone.
검색해 봐
My brain works better than a phone.
내 머리가 핸드폰보다는 낫지
Which sentence? Read it.
어떤 구절인데, 말해 봐
The first one.
첫 번째 구절
"Your servant has heard that whoever seeks a tree's vigorous growth..."
신이 듣기로 나무의 성장을 바라면
[Ten Recommendations to Emperor Taizong of Tang]
[태종 십사소]
Is this zhang ("to grow") or chang ("long")?
길 장이야, 어른 장이야?
What are you doing?
뭐 해?
Go back to your seat.
네 자리로 가
There was a line in the Classical Chinese text that we didn't understand,
이해 안 되는 문언문이 있어서
so we looked up the annotation.
주석을 좀 찾아봤어요
I don't care what you were doing.
이유가 무엇이든
Don't you know phones are strictly prohibited at school?
학교에서 핸드폰 소지 금지인 거 몰라?
No, we really didn't know it.
아니, 저희는 그냥
-We really only looked up the annotation. -Hand over your phone.
- 주석을 검색하느라… - 핸드폰 내놔
Hurry up.
어서
-We really weren't... -Hurry up!
- 저희 정말… - 얼른!
[Fight for your youth!]
[청춘이여, 힘차게 달려보자]
What are you looking at?
뭘 봐?
Get back to studying.
공부 안 해?
You two,
너희 둘
go out and reflect on your actions.
나가서 반성해
Go!
나가
Now!
어서
Hurry.
빨리 나가
We only looked up the annotation...
주석 찾아본 건데
[Fight for your youth!]
[청춘이여, 힘차게 달려보자]
What are you laughing at?
왜 웃어?
Study hard.
공부나 열심히 해
Boss,
대장
even if we're reflecting,
반성하는데
do we really have to run laps?
운동장까지 뛸 필요는 없잖아
Just think of it as training.
훈련이라고 생각하자
Why do you think Mr. Jin wouldn't believe us?
진 선생님은 왜 우리를 안 믿어 주실까?
You're really stupid.
멍청하긴
You actually expected him to believe us?
그분이 우리를 믿을 거라고 생각했어?
Wait, Boss.
잠깐만, 대장
What?
왜?
I ate something bad for lunch, and my stomach...
나 점심에 뭘 잘못 먹었는지 배가 좀…
Go.
가
Why is there always something with you?
정말 성가시다니까
It hurts so much. You...
왜 이렇게 아프지? 너…
Does yours not hurt?
넌 안 아파?
No.
응
Only you.
너만 유난이야
I seriously can't hold it anymore.
진짜 못 참겠어
Do you have any toilet paper?
너 휴지 있?
I...
나…
You've got some nerve.
너 간도 크다
I told you to bring it, but you didn't.
분명 주의 줬는데 안 가져오고
Then you had the guts to snitch to the teacher?
선생님한테 이르기까지 해?
I didn't.
아니야
-Stand still. -Boss.
- 똑바로 서 - 대장
Boss.
대장
-What? -Something's going on here.
- 왜? - 여기 와 봐
Why are you dodging?
어딜 피해?
Lift your head.
고개 들어!
-What's going on? -Listen to this.
- 무슨 상황이야 - 여기 와서 들어 봐
Do I have to beat you before you'll look up?
한 대 맞아야 고개 들 거야?
Do you believe
이 학교
that I'll make your life miserable at this school?
제대로 다니지 싫지?
Come here. Help me up.
이리 와서 나 좀 올려 줘
I didn't. I really didn't.
진짜 아니야
You dare sneak off and tell the teacher
네가 선생님한테 우리가 널 괴롭힌다고
that we've been bullying you?
일렀잖아
Me,
나
the top student in the entire grade.
이 학교 일등이야
Do you think they'd believe you?
선생님들이 널 믿을 것 같아?
Go.
가서
Pick it up.
주워와
Hurry up.
얼른
Say,
말해
"I'm a snitch."
나는 고자질쟁이다
Louder.
크게!
-I'm a snitch. -Bastards.
- 나는 고자질쟁이다 - 나쁜 자식
I'm a snitch.
나는 고자질쟁이다
What are you doing?
너 뭐야?
Alright.
됐어
It's alright now.
볼일 끝났어
Let's go back to class.
수업이나 들으러 가자
Did I say you could leave?
가긴 어딜 가?
Come with me to see Director Jin.
나랑 진 주임 뵈러 가자
I'd advise you to stay out of this.
쓸데없는 참견 안 하는 게 좋을걸
And even if we do go,
그리고 가봤자
who do you think they'll believe?
선생님들이 누굴 믿을 것 같아?
You lot still think you can play football?
너희 따위가 무슨 축구를 한다고
What a joke.
웃기시네
You lot are just a disgrace to the school.
나가서 학교 망신시키지 마
Who's the disgrace here?
너 지금 망신이라고 했어?
Let go!
이거 놔!
-Don't start a fight! -What are you doing?
- 하지 마 - 뭐 하는 거야?
-Back off! -You wanna fight?
- 비켜 - 지금 싸우겠다는 거야?
-What do you want? -What are you doing?
- 뭐? - 뭐 하는 거야?
-Get out of the way! -Go away!
- 비켜 - 저리 가
Hit me?
쳐 봐!
Think you can beat me?
이길 수 있겠어?
Let go of him!
그만해!
Boss, stop fighting!
대장, 그만해
Boss!
대장
D-Don't fight, Boss!
싸우지 마, 대장
Let go!
놔
Boss, don't fight!
대장, 싸우지 마
Let him go!
놔!
Boss, let him go!
대장, 그만해
They're fighting.
쟤들 싸우나 봐
Who's fighting?
누구랑 누군데?
What are you doing?
뭐 하는 거야?
Let's go get a teacher. Let's go.
얼른 선생님께 말씀드리자
Stop fighting! That's enough!
그만해, 싸우지 마!
-Let go! -That's enough, Boss!
- 놔 - 됐어, 대장
I was just memorizing vocabulary in the garden.
저 방금 화단에서 단어를 외우고 있었어요
Then I thought I'd eaten something bad at lunch,
그러다 배가 아파서
so I wanted to use the restroom.
화장실에 가려고 했는데
At the restroom entrance,
화장실 입구에서
I accidentally bumped into Qin Ao.
실수로 친아오랑 부딪혔거든요
Then he suddenly shoved me.
그런데 갑자기 저를 밀치는 거예요
I tried to block him, and he hit me.
막으려고 하니까 저를 막 때렸고요
Director, look,
보세요
he beat me up like this.
이렇게 맞았어요
Rao Di only got into the fight
라오디도
with them
저를 지켜 주려다
because he was trying to protect me.
쟤들이랑 싸우게 된 거예요
What are you talking about?
무슨 소리야?
Director,
선생님
they were the ones who started it.
분명 쟤들이 먼저 시작했어요
I saw them bullying another student.
다른 애를 괴롭히는 걸 제가 봤다고요
I was the one protecting someone.
제가 친구를 지켜 준 겁니다
So you're admitting you shoved him?
그래서 쟬 밀었니?
No!
아니에요
They hit Lin Lu first,
쟤들이 먼저 린루를 때려서
and I was only fighting back!
맞받아친 거예요
You're lying.
거짓말하지 마
How could I possibly hit someone?
내가 사람을 왜 때려?
The college entrance exam is coming up.
곧 대입 시험인데
My grades are so good.
내 성적에 싸우면
Getting into a fight would only hurt my exam results.
시험에 방해밖에 더 돼?
How could I possibly do that?
내가 그랬을 리가 없잖아
Impossible for you, but possible for me— is that it?
넌 그랬을 리 없고 난 그럴 수도 있다는 거야?
The whole school knows you have a bad temper.
네 성질 더러운 건 전교생이 다 아는데
You tell me if it's possible.
네가 아니라고?
Impossible!
아니야!
Director, I'll say it one more time—
선생님 다시 한번 말씀드리지만
I didn't start it!
제가 아니라면
I just didn't!
절대 아닌 겁니다
And I saw them bullying another student!
그리고 쟤들이 친구를 괴롭히는 걸 봤는데
Wasn't I supposed to stand up for him?
지켜 주는 게 당연하잖아요
Qin Ao,
친아오
what are you yelling about?
어디서 소리를 질러?
Instead of studying hard,
공부는 안 하고
you go around fighting and causing trouble.
사람 때리고 사고나 치고
Are you looking for a disciplinary record?
징계 받고 싶어?
Director, Wu Yunqi is really lying.
선생님, 정말 우윈치가 거짓말하는 거예요
The student they bullied is from Class 4, Grade 11.
얘네가 괴롭힌 애는 2학년 4반 학생이고요
Everyone calls him Little Mouse.
다들 샤오하오쯔라고 불러요
They got all his books dirty and stomped on them.
얘네가 걔 책을 밟고 더렵혔다고요
Director, if you don't believe us, you can go check.
못 믿으시겠으면 확인해 보세요
Mr. Wang.
왕 선생님
Director Jin.
네
Go to Class 4 and see if there's such a student.
4반에 가서 그런 애가 있는지 좀 봐 주세요
If so, bring him here.
있으면 이리로 데려오고요
And his backpack.
책가방도 같이 가져오세요
Okay.
네
Qin Ao, Lin Lu,
친아오, 린루
both of you stand properly with your heads down.
너희 둘, 고개 숙이고 똑바로 서 있어
Director Jin.
주임님
Hey,
저기
tell the Director the truth.
주임 선생님께 사실대로 말해
How did those two jerks bully you?
이 자식들이 널 어떻게 괴롭혔는지
It's okay. Don't be afraid. I'm here.
괜찮아, 내가 있으니 무서워하지 마
Student,
학생
what's your name?
이름이 뭐니?
Gu Yihao.
구이하오입니다
Gu Yihao,
구이하오 학생
you don't need to worry about anything.
아무 걱정하지 말고
Tell me,
나한테 말해 봐
just now during the break,
아까 쉬는 시간에 화장실에서
did anyone bully you outside the restroom?
누가 널 괴롭혔니?
No.
아니요
I didn't go downstairs
방금 쉬는 시간에
during the break.
전 내려가지 않았어요
No.
아니
You can
야
tell the truth. I'm here. It's okay.
사실대로 말해 내가 있잖아, 괜찮아
Tell the Director the truth.
선생님께 사실대로 말하라고
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
미안, 미안해
I wasn't lying.
나 거짓말 안 했어
Impossible! Give me your bag.
말도 안 돼, 네 책 줘 봐
These are not his books.
이거 얘 책 아니야
His name isn't on them.
이름도 없잖아
They must've switched his books, Director.
분명히 바꿔치기한 거예요 선생님
Wait, where are your books?
아니, 네 책 어딨어?
These aren't your books.
이거 네 책 아니잖아
Enough, both of you.
됐어, 그만 좀 해
Hey,
야, 너
what do you mean by this?
지금 뭐하는 거야?
They bullied you like that,
쟤네가 널 괴롭히는걸
and we stood up for you.
우리가 도와줬는데
Why are you doing this?
대체 왜 이러는 거야?
Qin Ao,
친아오
are you going to slander another student?
친구를 모함하겠다는 거야?
No,
아니에요
Director.
선생님
-Everything I said is... -Mr. Wang,
- 제 말… - 왕 선생님
send the three of them back to class,
얘네 셋은 교실로 돌려보내서 수업받게 하세요
alright?
알겠습니다
Pack up your things.
책가방 챙겨
Goodbye, Director.
안녕히 계세요, 선생님
Go back and focus on your lessons.
수업 잘 들어
Okay.
네
Jin Laoyao!
진 영감!
What do you mean by this?
지금 뭐 하는 거예요?
Just because they get good grades
쟤네는 공부를 잘하고
and we don't,
우리는 공부를 못하니까
you're covering for them, right?
쟤네만 감싸시는 거예요?
What did you just call me?
방금 나한테 뭐라고 했어?
Jin Laoyao!
진 영감이요!
Qin Ao,
친아오
instead of studying hard,
넌 공부는 안 하고
you falsely accuse other students,
친구를 모함한 데다
and now you're even disrespecting your teacher.
이제 선생님도 존중하지 않는구나
You...
너!
call your parents to come over.
전화해서 부모님 오시라고 해!
Fine!
하죠, 뭐
-Call them right now. -You think I'm scared?
- 빨리 전화해 - 제가 무서워할까 봐요?
Call them.
해!
Director Jin,
진 주임님
I'm Qin Ao's father.
친아오 아버지입니다
You're here.
오셨군요
These two students
이 두 학생이
were playing on their phones in class,
수업 시간에 몰래 핸드폰을 하고
got into a fight,
싸움까지 했습니다
and even slandered other students. And...
게다가 다른 학생을 모함하기까지 했고요
Director, our Lu
주임 선생님, 저희 린루는
isn't the type to bully other students.
친구를 괴롭히는 그런 아이가 아니에요
Why don't you look into it again?
다시 한번 확인해 주시겠어요?
We already have.
이미 다 확인했습니다
We brought in the student they mentioned
두 학생이 말한 그 학생을 불러서
and asked him clearly.
확실하게 물어봤는데
The things they said didn't happen.
그런 일은 없었다고 합니다
Tell me.
말해
What happened?
어떻게 된 거야?
How many times do I have to say it?
몇 번을 말해요?
We were just on our way to the restroom
린루랑 화장실 갔다가
when we saw another student being bullied.
누가 친구를 괴롭히는 걸 보고
We stepped in to help.
도와주러 간 거라고요
And they threw the first punch.
그리고 걔들이 먼저 때렸어요
Got it?
알아들어요?
We're not lying at all.
저희는 거짓말 안 했어요
Mr. Qin,
친아오 아버님
I hate to say this,
이런 말씀 드리긴 뭐하지만
but his slandering of other students is a matter of character.
다른 친구를 모함하는 건 인성의 문제입니다
He has to face disciplinary action!
반드시 징계를 받아야 해요
You're the one framing me!
선생님이 저한테 뒤집어씌우는 거잖아요
Qin Ao, watch your attitude!
친아오 너 지금 태도가 그게 뭐야?
He framed me, and I'm the one getting a demerit?
저한테 뒤집어씌우고 징계까지 주겠다잖아요
-Do you even deserve to be a teacher? -You!
- 그러고도 선생님 자격 있어요? - 너!
Watch how you speak!
무슨 말버릇이야!
Apologize to your teacher!
선생님께 사과드려!
I didn't do anything wrong! Why should I apologize?
제가 뭘 잘못했다고 사과해요?
Apologize now!
어서 사과 안 해!
You're getting more and more unruly.
점점 막나가는구나
Are you planning to quit school
너 공부할 생각 아예 없는 거지?
and go haul bricks on a construction site?
공사판 가서 벽돌이라도 나를래?
I'll say it one last time!
다시 한번 말하는데요!
I didn't lie, and I did nothing wrong!
저 거짓말도 안 했고 잘못한 것도 없어요!
You...
너!
Lin Lu!
린루
Look at his attitude!
쟤 하는 거 좀 보세요
How are we teachers supposed to teach him?
이러면 저희 교사들이 어떻게 가르칩니까?
-Director... -What should we...
- 주임 선생님 - 이걸 어떡하면…
Take them home
애들 데리고 가서
and discipline them yourselves.
잘 교육하십시오
Our teachers really can't manage them anymore.
저희 교사들은 정말 못 가르치겠습니다
Hello, Lin Lu. What's wrong?
응, 린루, 무슨 일이야?
Ms. Lin, something happened to my boss!
선생님, 대장이 큰일 났어요
What happened to Qin Ao?
친아오가 왜?
His dad just called and said
방금 친아오 아버지한테 전화 받았는데
he hasn't gone home yet.
아직도 집에 안 들어갔대요
Have you tried calling him?
휴대폰으로 연락해 봤어?
He got slapped at noon today.
점심때 한대 맞고
Then he just climbed over the wall and left the school.
바로 담 넘어서 학교를 나갔거든요
He didn't even take his phone.
휴대폰은 아예 안 가져갔어요
What should we do now?
저희 이제 어떡해요?
How about
아니면
I come to find you now,
저 지금 선생님한테 갈게요
and we can go look for him together?
같이 대장 찾으러 가요
No.
안 돼
It's too late now.
지금 너무 늦었어
Get some rest.
넌 일단 들어가
I'll go look for him.
내가 찾아볼게
-But he... -No buts.
- 하지만… - 됐어
Trust me.
선생님 믿어 줘
Hello. Qin Ao ran away from home.
여보세요, 친아오 집 나갔대요
I'll wait for you downstairs.
밑에서 기다릴게요
Let's go look for him together.
같이 찾아요
Okay.
네
Qin Ao!
친아오
Did you find him?
찾았어요?
No. I'll check over there.
아니요, 난 저쪽 찾아볼게요
Okay.
네
Where else could Qin Ao be?
얘가 어디로 간 걸까요?
We've looked everywhere.
갈만한 곳은 다 찾아봤는데
I just remembered.
아, 맞다
They have a secret hideout at school.
애들이 학교에 비밀 아지트가 있어요
Come with me.
따라와요
It's here.
바로 여기예요
This is their secret hideout.
여기가 걔네 아지트거든요
Qin Ao.
친아오
Nothing.
없어요
Not here either.
여기도 없어요
Even without proof,
확인해 보진 않았지만
I believe
난 친아오가
Qin Ao was wrongly accused.
그러지 않았다는 걸 믿어요
When you're a teenager,
사춘기 때는
there's nothing worse than being falsely accused—
억울한 일을 당하면 정말 싫어하잖아요
especially by the people closest to you.
특히 가장 가까운 사람한테요
When I was little,
어렸을 때
my dad always said that
아빠가 늘 그러셨어요
when he got back from his business trip,
출장 갔다가 돌아오면
he'd take me to the zoo.
동물원에 데려가 줄게
If I could place first in my year,
전교 1등만 하면
he'd buy me balloons,
풍선도 사 주고
toys,
장난감도 사 주고
and everything I liked.
네가 좋아하는 건 뭐든지 다 사줄게
But he never once kept his word.
하지만 단 한 번도 지킨 적이 없었어요
He said he was busy?
바쁘다고 하던가요?
So
그래서
I saved up my allowance
난 용돈을 모아서
and bought all the things I liked.
좋아하는 걸 다 샀어요
But when he saw them,
근데 아빠가 그걸 보고
he accused me of stealing his money to buy them.
내가 돈을 훔쳤다면서
He threw everything away.
전부 다 버린 거 있죠
He didn't believe me.
날 믿어주지 않았어요
It's always been like this.
늘 그랬죠
What happened after that?
그래서 어떻게 됐나요?
Later, even when he
나중에 차 안에서
found his money in the car,
잃어버렸던 돈을 찾았는데도
he didn't apologize to me.
나한테 사과하지 않았어요
He might not even remember it now.
아마 기억도 못할 걸요
But I still remember.
근데 난 아직도 기억에 생생해요
The feeling of being wrongly accused
억울하게 오해받는 기분은
is like a blade cutting into you.
칼로 살을 베는 것처럼
The pain stays with you for a long time.
오래 기억에 남거든요
Wang Fa.
코치님
We have to find Qin Ao
우리 꼭 친아오를 찾아서
and tell him
말해 줘야 해요
that he deserves to be believed.
걘 믿음을 받을 가치가 있는 아이라고
Don't worry.
걱정 마요
We'll find him.
꼭 찾을 수 있을 거예요
Why did it suddenly start raining?
갑자기 비가 오네요
Let's head back.
이제 들어가죠
Searching aimlessly at night
밤에 무작정 찾는다고
isn't going to help.
해결될 일이 아니에요
We'll keep looking in the morning.
내일 아침에 더 찾아보고
If we still can't find him after 24 hours, we'll call the police.
24시간 지나면 경찰에 신고해요
Okay.
그래요
I'll call Qin Ao's father.
그럼 친아오 아버지한테 전화해 볼게요
Ms. Lin.
린 선생님
Did you find him?
친아오 찾으셨습니까?
What?
네?
Who knows where he ran off to?
얘가 어딜 간 거야
I'm sorry
죄송합니다
for causing you trouble.
선생님께 폐를 끼쳤네요
Okay.
네
Don't worry.
걱정 마세요
If I find him,
애 찾으면
I'll let you know immediately.
바로 연락드리겠습니다
Okay.
네
Got it, Uncle.
네, 알겠습니다
Qin Ao's dad said he'd searched everywhere.
친아오 아버지가 여기저기 다 찾아보셨대요
Logically,
원래대로라면
he shouldn't have gone very far.
그렇게 먼 곳까지는 안 갔을 텐데요
I checked, and there are a few internet cafes nearby.
근처에 PC방이 몇 군데 더 있던데
We can look around there.
거기도 한번 찾아보죠
But you look terrible.
근데 안색이 너무 안 좋아요
Do you want to take a break?
좀 쉬었다가 찾을까요?
I'm fine.
저 괜찮아요
Lin Lu?
린루예요
Coach, Coach,
코치님, 코치님
my cousin's family works in construction.
저희 사촌 형이 공사 쪽 일을 하는데요
He just told me
방금 연락이 왔어요
he thinks he saw Boss
훙징 신촌 공사장에서
at the Hongjing New Village construction site.
대장을 봤다고요
Okay, we'll head there now.
알았어, 지금 갈게
I've called a cab.
차 불렀어요
Let's go.
얼른 가요
You see, he first says,
'거기 둬요, 샹린 아줌마'
"Leave it here, Xianglin's Wife."
먼저 이렇게 말했어
The tone here is much harsher.
이 어투가 더 딱딱하잖아
So his tone
그러니까 말투에서
shows his dissatisfaction and disgust towards her.
샹린댁에 대한 불만과 혐오가 드러나는 거야
But if he'd said, "Xianglin's Wife, just leave it there,"
만약 '거기 두면 돼요'라고 했다면
wouldn't it sound a bit more polite?
좀 더 예의 있어 보이지 않니?
So by comparing the two ways of saying it,
그러니까 둘을 비교해 보면
we can see the strong feelings expressed by the author.
그의 강렬한 감정이 드러나는 거지
[Okay, we'll head there now.]
[네, 지금 갈게요]
So, pay attention to this part.
그러니 이 부분은 주의하도록 해
Not bad.
좋아
Your accuracy rate is very high.
정답률이 아주 높네
[Found Qin Ao. Let's go.]
[친아오 찾았대, 가자]
-Lin Lu? Lin Lu. -Lin Lu.
- 린루, 린루 - 린루
Are you okay?
너 괜찮아?
What's wrong?
왜 그래?
-I'm dizzy... really dizzy... -What happened?
- 어지러워요 - 왜?
I feel very dizzy.
머리가 어지러워요
What's wrong?
괜찮아?
He probably has low blood sugar again,
얘 저혈당 증세가 또 온 것 같아요
ma'am.
선생님
How about I take him to the infirmary right now?
제가 양호실로 데려가도 될까요?
-Okay, go quickly. -Okay, okay.
- 어, 빨리 가 - 네
-Thank you, ma'am. -I'm so dizzy...
- 감사합니다, 선생님 - 어지러워
It's fine. Let's go.
괜찮아, 가자
Be careful.
조심해
Be careful. Careful.
조심, 조심해
Thank you, ma'am. Goodbye.
감사합니다, 선생님 저희 가 볼게요
Everyone, self-study now.
다들 자습해
How did you know?
어떻게 알았어?
From my phone.
핸드폰 문자
Didn't Jin Laoyao confiscate your phone?
네 핸드폰은 진 영감한테 뺏겼잖아
[Teachers' Office 3]
[교사 사무실 3]
Who told you I only had one?
핸드폰이 그거 하나뿐이라고 누가 그래?
[Class 6, Grade 12]
[고3 6반]
This is my mom's spare phone.
이거 우리 엄마 예비 폰이야
Now, let's go over
자, 다음은
the strategies for grammar cloze questions.
문법 빈칸 채우기 요령이야
First, these questions involve verbs,
문법 빈칸 채우기는 동사로 나뉘고
which can be divided into finite and non-finite verbs.
동사는 또 술어와 비술어로 나뉜다
Finite verbs involve tense,
술어는 또 시제를 봐야 하는데
and tense includes past and perfect tenses.
시제는 과거와 완료로 나눌 수 있어
Everyone, turn your textbooks to
자, 다들 교과서 펼쳐
-page 111. -Chen Jianghe.
- 111페이지 - 천장허
-Do the second multiple-choice question.
- 선택 문제의 두 번째 문제
Sir.
선생님
What's wrong?
왜?
My stomach hurts.
저 배가 아파서 그러는데
I need to go to the restroom.
화장실 가도 될까요?
Go.
가
Come back quickly.
빨리 다녀와
The rest of you, continue.
너희는 계속 풀어
Everyone, pay attention to the changes in the liquid in the test tube.
시험관 속 액체의 변화를 잘 관찰해 봐
In our last class,
지난 수업에서
we talked about radicles and seedlings,
어린 뿌리와 어린 싹에 대해 배웠는데
but many of you couldn't distinguish
어린 뿌리와 어린 싹이 어느 부위를 말하는지
which parts they refer to.
다들 헷갈려 하니까
Today, I'll explain them
오늘 다시
carefully again.
자세히 설명해 줄게
First, we need to know that
우선
-radicles and seedlings -Cover for me.
- 유근과 유묘는 - 너 좀 막아줘
contain small amounts of gibberellins
지베렐린과
and cytokinins.
사이토키닌을 함유하고 있고
And they also have small amounts of some other...
동시에 소량의 다른 물질들도 함유하고 있어
-Ma'am! Ma'am! -Ma'am!
- 선생님
-He's not feeling well.
- 푸신수가 아파요 - 푸신수가 아프대요
He wants to go to the infirmary.
양호실에 데려가도 될까요?
What's wrong?
어디가 아픈데?
-His stomach hurts. -His head hurts.
- 위요 - 머리요
Where does it hurt?
어디가 아프다고?
-His... His head hurts. -His stomach hurts.
- 머리 아프대요 - 위 아프대요
Where exactly is he hurt?
도대체 어디가 아픈 거야?
Ma'am, they both hurt a little.
선생님, 저 둘 다 아파요
So much trouble. Go, go.
정말 유난이야, 얼른 가
-Go, go. -Okay, okay.
- 가라고 - 네
-Such a handful. -Thank you, ma'am. Thank you.
- 정신 사나워 - 감사합니다, 선생님
We'll be right back.
금방 돌아올게요
I really can't hold on anymore.
진짜 못 참겠어
-Be right back, ma'am.
- 금방 올게요 - 금방 오겠습니다
Alright, the rest of you, don't be distracted.
자, 다른 학생들은 신경 쓰지 말고
Let's continue our class.
수업 계속하자
[Class 1, Grade 12]
[고3 1반]
Open your workbooks.
문제집 보자
Turn to Chapter 8, Section 8.
제8장 제8절
Read carefully.
자세히 읽어 봐
Qin!
친아오
Are you done with your work?
하던 일 다 끝냈어?
Done!
네, 끝냈습니다
Come on, get down!
이리 와
Help unload the cement from the cart.
가서 시멘트 내리게
Coming!
네
[Beware of the Water]
[낙석 조심]
Be careful.
조심해
[Caution: Fall Hazard]
[추락 조심]
Qin Ao!
친아오
Wait.
거기 서
[Caution: Fall Hazard]
[추락 조심]
Coach, Ms. Lin,
코치님, 린 선생님
why are you here?
왜 여기 계세요?
We should be asking you that.
그건 우리가 물어볼 말이야
Why are you here?
너 왜 여기 있어?
Just leave.
가세요
Stop worrying about me.
저 신경 쓰지 말고
My dad is right.
저희 아빠 말씀이 맞아요
I was born to carry cement and tighten screws.
전 그냥 시멘트 나르고 나사나 조일 팔자인가 봐요
Just go.
가주세요
Boss!
대장
Qin Ao!
친아오
-Qin Ao! -Qin Ao.
- 친아오
-Qin Ao! -Come here.
- 이리 와
Where have you been?
어딜 가려고
We've been worried sick about you.
다들 걱정했잖아
Don't worry about me.
나 좀 내버려 둬
I mean it. Don't worry about me.
진짜야, 신경 꺼 줘
Hit me, yell at me—I don't care.
때리든 욕하든 마음대로 하고
Just go.
그냥 가 줘
I think you're really asking for a beating.
너 진짜 한 대 맞아야겠네
What are you talking about?
무슨 헛소리야?
Since when did you become such a coward?
왜 이렇게 쫄았어?
We're all here.
우리가 있잖아
We'll go with you to see Jin Laoyao.
같이 진 영감 찾으러 가자
Ms. Lin.
린 선생님
Take them and go.
애들 데리고 가세요
This is a construction site.
여긴 공사장이에요
It's crowded
사람도 많고 복잡하고
and really messy.
지저분한걸요
Qin Ao!
친아오
Aren't we a team?
우리 같은 팀 아니었어?
Yeah. Worst case, we all haul bricks together!
맞아, 까짓것 같이 벽돌 나르지, 뭐
Right. I'll go get hard hats.
그래, 안전모 가져올게
I'll work with you, Boss.
나도 같이 할게, 대장
Come on, come on.
자
I'll help you, Boss.
내가 도와줄게
Look at you, like a drowned rat.
지금 꼴이 꼭 물에 빠진 생쥐 같네
Just looking at you ticks me off.
보기만 해도 열받아
Give me a hand.
이것 좀 들어
What are you doing?
뭐 하는 거야?
Let go! Let go!
다 놔!
Sorry! Sorry!
죄송합니다, 죄송해요
They're students from Hongjing No. 8 High School.
얘네 훙징 제8고등학교 학생들입니다
I'm their teacher.
제가 담당 교사고요
We're here for a work-study program.
여기서 근로 체험 활동을 좀 하려고요
We're doing it for free.
전부 무료로요
We just need you to write us a certificate later.
대신 나중에 저희한테 증명서 발급해 주시면 돼요
Don't mention it.
아닙니다
Ms. Lin reacted so fast.
린 선생님, 반응 진짜 빠르네
-Hurry. -Come on.
- 자 - 옮겨
Come on, come on.
이리 줘
Be careful, everyone.
다들 조심해
What a bunch of idiots.
바보들 같으니라고
Take it easy.
조심해
Yeah,
그러게
a bunch of idiots.
다들 바보 같지
They insist on calling you "Boss"
굳이 널 대장이라고 부르고
and helping you haul bricks.
굳이 벽돌 나르는 걸 돕겠다고 하잖아
Do you really have the heart to abandon them?
저런 애들을 정말 버릴 거야?
It's not that I want to abandon them.
제가 버리려는 게 아니에요
It's that I don't want to go back.
그냥 돌아가기 싫어서요
My dad's always looked down on me.
아빠는 항상 절 무시하셨어요
I wasn't lying. I...
저 거짓말 안 했거든요
I really wasn't lying.
정말 아닌데
Why won't anyone believe me?
왜 아무도 절 안 믿어주는 거죠?
We believe you.
우린 널 믿어
Me,
나랑
Coach Wang,
왕 코치님
and your buddies here—
그리고 네 친구들
we all believe you.
우리 모두 널 믿어
Qin Ao, don't run away from this.
친아오, 도망치지 마
You should prove to those
널 믿지 않는 사람들한테
who don't believe you
네가 직접 증명해 보여야지
that they're wrong.
그 사람들이 틀렸다는 걸
♪ The night sky and starlight ♪
♪ 밤하늘의 별빛 ♪
♪ Secret words falling into my palm ♪
♪ 손바닥 위로 떨어진 은밀한 속삭임, 속삭임 ♪
Will they ever admit it?
정말 알아 줄까요?
♪ Unraveling the mystery ♪
♪ 수수께끼를 풀고 ♪
They will.
그럴 거야
♪ It was you who gave me this brilliance ♪
♪ 내게 눈부신 빛을 선물한 건 너야, 바로 너 ♪
♪ Lasting memories ♪
♪ 기나긴 기억 ♪
♪ The distance that brings our dreams closer ♪
♪ 꿈과 가까워진 거리 그 거리 ♪
♪ To run toward you ♪
♪ 너에게 달려가기 위해 ♪
♪ I keep practicing with no turning back ♪
♪ 난 거침없이 연습 또 연습해 ♪
♪ There's nothing to fear ♪
♪ 두려울 게 없어 ♪
♪ Because you're with me ♪
♪ 네가 있으니까 ♪
♪ The light shimmers ♪
♪ 희미한 빛이 비쳐 ♪